Regulations and laws can affect the day to day operations of many organizations.
One example of a law with a broad impact is the general data protection regulation.
GDPR
which affords data protection and control to individuals within
the territorial boundaries of the EU regardless of citizenship.
As another example in the United States,
patient medical information is governed by the health care insurance,
Portability and Accountability Act of 1996
HIPA
and must be closely guarded
from the information security perspective.
A high standard of professionalism is expected
in safeguarding data on the patient's behalf.
Information security is based on trust and credibility.
If something goes wrong,
the stakeholders trust evaporates and organization's
credibility is damaged sometimes without cure.
HIPA
A also carries significant criminal and financial penalties for non
compliance for both the organization and the individuals involved.
Fortunately,
there are published frameworks or standards to guide
the organizational policies that support the compliance effort.
Many departments or work groups
within the organization implement procedures that
detail how they complete day to day tasks while remaining compliant.
Among these groups is the International Organization for Standardization
ISO
O
ISO is an international standards body. One of the standards that is
o publishes is how to destroy data in a secure fashion.